A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs, Office Files of Joseph E. Slater FA619
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs, Office Files of Joseph E. Slater
1957-1967
Rockefeller Archive Center
Stone, Shepard
Nielsen, Waldemar A.
Slater, Joseph E.
Ford Foundation
Gordon, Stanley
Catalano, Richard
FA619
21.2 Cubic Feet
The files from the Office of Joseph E. Slater, cover the years 1957 to 1967, and consist primarily of reports, correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and notes. The material has been arranged into six series. There was no discernible order within the series; therefore, the processor imposed an artificial order on their arrangement. Material falling into the following categories has been removed and transferred to the appropriate records groups in the Ford Foundation Archives: -Unpublished staff and consultant reports -Speeches by Mr. Slater and other Ford Foundation staff -Office of Reports (OR) publications -Budget papers Listings of the staff and consultant reports, speeches, and OR publications that were removed from the papers are appended to this register. The Archives maintains an index (#39) of budget papers. For additional information regarding Mr. Slater and the International Affairs program, the researcher should consult Slater's oral history.
Arrangement
The office files of Joseph E. Slater are divided into six series:
I. CHRONOLOGICAL FILES
II. GEOGRAPHIC FILES
III. MEETING FILES
IV. ORGANIZATION FILES
V. SUBJECT FILES
VI. TRIP NOTES
Some of the series, or items among particular series, are interrelated. When this is the case, cross references are indicated at the head of the series, and/or are listed after the individual folder listings.
Scope and Contents
The office files of Joseph E. Slater span the years 1957 to 1967. During this time, Mr. Slater held various positions in the International Affairs (IA) program, ultimately becoming Program Officer in Charge. The files are comprised of many types of documents totaling 21.5 linear feet: reports, drafts, background papers, strategy papers, requests for grant action, correspondence, memoranda, minutes, and notes. This material stems from Slater's involvement in a wide range of activities within and outside the Foundation: conferences, committees, program reviews, meetings, world-wide travel, and day-to-day Foundation activity. The files are particularly strong with regard to the following topics:
Atlantic partnership; European community; Economic development; Relationship between developed and developing countries; East-West relations; Asia and the Pacific; International organizations; International communications; Science and technology; World affairs education
In 1962, Slater served as Study Director of the Special Committee appointed by the Board of Trustees, and its Chairman, John J. McCloy. This committee issued a report, "Directives and Terms of Reference for the 1960's". The working papers of the Committee, drafts of its report, and four volumes of supporting material, which are arranged in a separate collection, are complemented by material in Slater's files.
"Directives and Terms of Reference for the 1960's" reviewed the Foundation's program activities from 1950 to 1961, and recommended a revised set of policies and programs for the decade ahead. The four regions of concern to the IA program were: the United States, the Atlantic community, the Pacific, and the international community. Overall, the goals were twofold: to solidify political, economic, and social foundations within each region, and to develop mediums for the coordination and cooperation of their policies in the international arena. An overriding objective was to reduce global tensions.
The bulk of Slater's files document the actions taken by the IA program as a result of the recommendations made in the Committee's Report. The contents of Slater's files may be enhanced if viewed in connection with the report, its supporting material, and with the working files of the Committee. Slater's files which predate the Report's publication (1957-1961), are largely devoted to U.S foreign economic policy, and Atlantic and European affairs. To this end, they are integral to the later material.
In the early 1960s, the building of an Atlantic partnership was a Foundation priority. The main objective of the partnership was to strengthen and unify the European Community to the point where it could be an equal partner to the United States. Another basic principle was the establishment of links between the developed countries of the "free world" and the developing countries.
The files demonstrate lA's interest in meeting the goals of the Atlantic partnership. They document the support given to European initiatives in economic development and integration, higher education, and to the encouragement of relationships between Western Europe and the developing countries.
The files which cover Europe and the Atlantic partnership are not restricted to an individual series. Slater's trips abroad, inter-Foundation activity, and external conferences and organizations all have a bearing on this topic. Of particular significance is the material related to the following individuals, organizations, and subjects:
Individuals
Dowling, Walter; Gordey, Michel; Huntley, James H.; Kohnstamm, Max; Moore, Ben T.; Neuman, Robert; Schaetzel, J. Robert
Organizations
Atlantic Institute (1); European Productivity Agency
Subjects
Business and management education; Economic development and integration; European travel; Economic and social development of Latin America; Young Leaders project (2)
A cohesive Atlantic community was also important to the East- West relationship. The files contain a variety of documentation with regard to this topic. In the late 1950s, IA began to stimulate international cultural activities as a means of expanding East-West contacts. Slater's notes of his trip to the Soviet Union in 1964 indicate the Foundation's concern for East-West issues. A letter from Zbignew Brzezinski (March 23, 1967) reports on the mood in Europe toward East-West issues, and makes recommendations to the Foundation for programs in this area.
For a more detailed account of the topics having to do with Europe, the Atlantic, and the East-West relationship, consult the individual folder listings, located elsewhere in this register.
In 1958, Slater organized an informal group of businessmen, academicians, and former government officials from outside the Foundation to study foreign economic policy, particularly the role of private enterprise in its implementation. The files of the "Foreign Economic Policy Project" include correspondence, reports, memoranda, agenda material, and minutes. Subsequently, Henry Heald (then President of the Foundation) appointed an ad hoc committee (Shepard Stone, Neil Chamberlain, and John Howard) to examine, on behalf of Foundation interests, the issue of economic cooperation in the foreign arena. Material from Slater's study group was used by this committee. (3)
During Slater's tenure, IA expanded to include the developed countries of the Pacific, particularly Japan; and to a lesser degree Australia. IA activities were designed to bring Japanese institutions into the mainstream of western democratic activity, namely that of the Atlantic partnership. The material generated by Herbert Passin, Foundation consultant on Japan throughout the 1960s, documents the Foundation's activities in Japan during that decade. Also included are a few pieces on the Foundation's involvement in Korea during that time.
Although Latin America is not traditionally one of IA's regional interests, Slater was involved in certain Latin American projects. His files include material from a Foundation study to establish a "House of the Americas" (Casa de las Americas). This study was a building block in the creation of the Center for Inter-American Relations. (See PA67-285) Included in the files are the project's final proposal by Philip Van Slyck, and commentary on the project by Latin American scholars.
Slater worked as a consultant to the late Senator Jacob Javits in the establishment of ADELA - the Atlantic Community Development Group for Latin America (P A63-218). Its goal was to encourage multilateral private investment in Latin America. A long-term goal was the establishment of a Latin American Common Market. Slater's correspondence with Javits regarding Latin American economic integration is included in the files. Former President of Colombia, Alberto Lleras Camargo, was also involved in this project.
From March 13 to 17, 1963, Slater attended a seminar sponsored by the Council on Religion and International Affairs entitled, "Intervention and the American Purpose: Cuba 1962". Top government officials who had been involved in the Cuban Missile Crisis were among those who participated in the discussions. The file from this conference includes Slater's handwritten notes of sessions with Paul Nitze, then Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security Affairs; Roger Hilsman, then Director of Intelligence and Research Department of State; and Harlan Cleveland, then Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs. The file also includes a copy of a memorandum from Slater to Stone in which Slater conveys some of the discussion's conclusions with regard to the impact of the crisis on the Atlantic alliance.
In 1962, the Council on Foreign Relations (CFR) received an IA grant (P A62-365), for studies concerning the development of the Atlantic partnership and the challenge presented by Communist China. CFR, in turn, established two projects - The United States and China in World Affairs and Atlantic Policy Studies. These projects were comprised of steering committees and smaller study and discussion groups. Slater's files contain many of the working and background papers used by these committees and study groups, and supplement the material in the grant file, which is on microfilm. As a member of the Council on Foreign Relations, Slater also participated in CFR studies which examined the relationship between science and international relations. These files include material produced by two discussion groups, Science and the National Interest and Science and Foreign Policy.
(Slater's files also document lA's interest in exploring the role of science in world affairs, particularly the impact of scientific development on international relations. These files include drafts of reports by Foundation staff and consultants, inter-office memoranda, and correspondence from individuals in the field.)
During Slater's tenure, the IA program was concerned with strengthening the United Nations. The files include preparatory material for a study done by Lawrence Finkestein on this subject. Some Foundation grants to the Brookings Institution were designated for work in this area. The files contain material on two Brookings' projects: (1) the United Nations Policy Studies Program, a committee on which Slater served, and (2) the strengthening of the United Nations' specialized agencies, notably the U.N.'s Institute for Training and Research.
The Foundation's interest in the field of international communications prompted it to participate in the creation of the International Broadcast Institute (1966-1967). The files contain Slater's correspondence with those closely involved with this project - Louis Cowan, David Webster and Sig Mickelson. There is also correspondence documenting international support and recommendations for the establishment of the institute from individuals associated with the media, as well as from professionals in other fields. The group includes Michel Gordey (Le Monde, France), Aurelio Peccei (Olivetti, Italy), Robert McDonald (Vice President, Foreign Policy Association), George Probst, (Chairman, Broadcasting Foundation of America), William Benton and Maurice Mitchell (Publisher and Chairman, and President, Encyclopedia Britannica). Finally, there are numerous internal and external reports which chronicle the development of the institute.
The IA program supported the study of arms control. The files include correspondence relating to a consultants' report by Eric Stevenson and John Teeple, "Research in Arms Control and Disarmament, 1960-1963". Memoranda and correspondence relating to Ernest Lefever's consultancy work in this field are also included.
There is material that demonstrates the Foundation's interest in the caliber of the United States' public service. Of particular interest, is an 8-page letter from Slater to John McCloy (January 1960), on the importance of strong public leadership. The letter contains possible ways to improve the public service career system.
Citizen Education in World Affairs was an IA study to improve adult knowledge of, and participation in world affairs. The memoranda of James Huntley (staff) and Calvin Nichols (consultant) contain information on the Foundation's support of World Affairs Councils throughout the United States, and of other IA activity to promote world affairs education.
Material from the Foundation's 1962 study, Personnel for Overseas Development, is included. This study examined the qualifications of personnel from the developed world, working in developing countries. Both private and public sector organizations were considered.
The files contain material from IA program reviews that took place in 1966 and 1967. They include strategy papers and memoranda regarding many of the topics already mentioned, for example, the Atlantic community, international economic cooperation, relationships between developed and developing countries, rising young leaders, the United Nations, and international scientific cooperation. Two draft reports, "International Order, International Institutions and the United Nations" and "The United Nations, International Institutions and International Order", contain commentary by Henry Kissinger, then at the Center for International Affairs, Harvard University; and Robert Manning, Editor, The Atlantic Monthly.
The "review" files also contain individual country reports. These include several papers on the People's Republic of China. They demonstrate the Foundation's interest in opening lines of communication with Mainland China. One means was to stimulate contemporary Chinese studies in the United States and abroad. In a memorandum (Nov 8, 1966) to Slater, Kenneth T. Young (the Asia Society) suggested a "Program for Contemporary Chinese Affairs" for the years 1970-1995.
Finally, in addition to the extensive memoranda of James Huntley and Herbert Passin, Slater's files also include grantee-status memoranda by Charles McVicker (IA consultant, 1966-1967) documenting a range of IA interests; and some European trip notes of Stanley Gordon, Richard Catalano, Waldemar Nielson, and Shepard Stone, colleagues in the IA program. Mr. Stone was Director of IA from 1955 to 1965. Stone and Slater collaborated on many projects, and shared a close professional relationship. In addition to his trip notes, Slater's files also contain some of Stone's correspondence and memoranda.(4) -------------------------------------------------------------------
NOTES:
(1) The Atlantic Institute should not be confused with the Atlantic Foundation. The creation of a Foundation never came to fruition. However, the material generated by its proposals are located in these files.
(2) The Young Leaders project was a talent scout system to build a community of potential leaders who embraced the European- Atlantic concept.
(3) Slater's committee was also referred to as the Private Initiative for International Economic Cooperation for Growth and Freedom. The goal of the ad-hoc committee as stated by Heald, was a United States and free world program of economic cooperation for growth and freedom.
(4) See Ford Foundation reports #002804, "Citizen Education in World Affairs: 1) The Foreign Policy Association 2) The World Affairs Councils" and #002581, "Report of Committee on Citizen Education in World Affairs", for more information on this topic.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph E. Slater, Program Officer in Charge of the International Affairs (IA) Program from January 1967 until November 1967, also held the following positions:
11/1961-12/1966 Associate Director, International Affairs Program (IA)
11/1961-7/1962 Study Director, Special Committee to review Ford Foundation's operations and future policies and programs
8/1957-10/1960 Program Associate, International Affairs Program (IA)
During Mr. Slater's tenure at the Foundation, he took several leaves of absence:
1961 Department of State, Deputy Assistant Secretary for Educational and Cultural Affairs
1960-61 Development Loan Fund, Assistant Managing Director
1958-59 The President's Committee to Study the United States Military Assistance Program, Executive Secretary
Before joining the Foundation in 1957, Mr. Slater was Chief Economist at the Creole Petroleum Corporation (Standard Oil Co., N.J.) in Caracas, Venezuela; and Executive Director of the Creole Foundation, also in Caracas. Prior to his work in Venezuela, Mr. Slater held various posts in the United States Government, both in the U.S and abroad.
Mr. Slater was born in Salt Lake City, Utah on August 17, 1922. He graduated with honors from the University of California at Berkeley in 1943 with an A.B. degree in Economics.
Mr. Slater resigned from the Foundation in November 1967. From 1967 to 1972 he was President of the Salk Institute, La Jolla, California; and from 1969 to 1986, President and Chief Executive Officer of the Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies. In 1986, he assumed the post of Chairman of the John J. McCloy International Center in New York City.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Completion of a use agreement is required prior to providing scholarly access. See RAC Head of Reference (or applicable designee) for details.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation's future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford's international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee's report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation's aspirational goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Sketch - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
The Ford Foundation's expansion era (1950-1965) began when the Gaither Study Committee Report placed "peace" as the area of top priority for the Foundation and set the Ford Foundation on a global course. Board Chair Henry Ford II writing in the 1951 Annual Report of the Foundation, identified "the danger of war" as the "the prime threat to human welfare today." Under the leadership of the three Ford Foundation presidents in this period-- Paul Hoffman, H. Rowan Gaither and Henry Heald--and several key trustees, notably the two seriatim chairs, John J. McCloy and Julius A. Stratton, the Foundation programs were largely informed by the post-World War II desire to avoid nuclear war and promote greater understanding among the world's peoples, strengthening of the United Nations, and enhancing both private and public American participation in world affairs. The strong board presence of university presidents and former leaders of postwar reconstruction efforts in Europe also helped to inform Ford's approach to building the field of peace and international security in the United States and encouraged extensive overseas activities.
For example, the first three presidents of the expanded Foundation ranged from government and business leadership experience to academic and nonprofit: Paul Hoffman (at Ford, 1950-1953) ran the Marshall Plan in Europe; H. Rowan Gaither Staffer (1948-1953), President (1953-1956) and Trustee (1956-1958) had MIT and Rand experience; Henry Heald, former president, Illinois Institute of Technology and New York University, President (1956-1966). The trustees also ran the leadership gamut from government and nonprofits to academic: Trustee John J. McCloy (from 1953; chair, 1959-1965) was assistant Secretary of War during World War II and chairman of the Council on Foreign Relations; and Trustee Julius A. Stratton (Trustee from 1955; chair, 1966-1970) was president of MIT.
When Ford became an international foundation in 1950, it had a small staff and operated through separate funds. The expansive period in the 1950s and 1960s resulted in a large number of field offices, which increased Ford's global footprint. Support focused on a mix of US university-based programs for research and training; think-tanks for policy-oriented meetings and policy research; and action projects specifically in less developed countries. The Foundation's focus on peace, freedom, and democracy played out against the Cold War backdrop for scientific and military competition between the United States, the Soviet Union and China.
Under President Hoffman, the Foundation's work was organized by the areas identified in the Gaither Committee Report: Area One, the Establishment of Peace; Area Two, The Strengthening of Democracy; Area Three, The Strengthening of the Economy; Area Four, Education in a Democratic Society; and Area Five, Individual Behavior and Human Relations.